export default  Civic_Ministry_2015 = [
    {
        id: "h1",
        Number_of_Questions: "60 Questions",
        Time_Allowed: "1 hour",
      },
    {
        id: 1,
        question: "If someone practices courage, he becomes courageous. This idea explains that:",
        options: [
        "Virtue develops in nature",
        "Virtue develops as a result of practice",
        "Someone is created naturally courageous",
        "There is no relationship between courage and practice"
        ],
        correct_option: "Virtue develops as a result of practice",
        explanation:"A civic virtue is a reasoned devotion or commitment that all citi-zens of a given state are expected to discharge or fulfil.\n"+
        "It is pro-foundly applied or practised if and only if citizens and students persistently internalised the aforementioned and other moral vir-tues, thereby incorporating them into their behaviour or conduct."
        },
        
        {
        id: 2,
        question: "One of the following describes the vice character of a person.",
        options: [
        "dishonesty ",
        "Courage",
        "Compassion",
        "Generosity"
        ],
        correct_option: "dishonesty ",
        explanation: 'The term "vice" is often associated with bad habits. Vices are the polar opposite of virtues, and they refer to evil or personal corruption.\n'+ 
        "For instance, dishonesty, cowardice, or selfishness, injustice, and so on."
        },
        
        {
        id: 3,
        question: "The behaviour and attitude of not telling or accepting lies is:-",
        options: [
        "Courage",
        "Compassion",
        "Generosity",
        "Honesty "
        ],
        correct_option: "Honesty",
        explanation:"Honesty is defined as the behaviour and attitude of not telling or accepting lies"
        },
        
        {
        id: 4,
        question: "A person who works hard within hardships develops the quality of:-",
        options: [
        "Generosity",
        "Courage  ",
        "Honesty",
        "Compassion"
        ],
        correct_option: "Courage",
        explanation:"Courage is the attitude of confronting and dealing with what is perceived to be difficult or painful rather than avoiding it; it is a "+
        " quality of being fearless or brave. It means trying again and again until you succeed.\n"+
        "It is the determination to work hard despite any odds or obstacles that may exist."
        },
        
        {
        id: 5,
        question: "If you devout your time, energy and resource for the welfare of others, the quality of virtue you develop is:-",
        options: [
        "Generosity ",
        "Honesty",
        "Compassion",
        "Courage"
        ],
        correct_option: "Generosity",
        explanation:"Generosity:is the moral disposition to expend time, effort, and re-sources for the benefit of others."
        },
        {
            id: 6,
            question: "The following statements describe the importance of virtue ethics, except:",
            options: [
            " It doesn't help to find out the purpose of life.",
            " It is helpful for identification of right and wrong.",
            " Enables someone to accomplish his responsibility.",
            " Helps to avoid problems of social evils from our life."
            ],
            correct_option: "It doesn't help to find out the purpose of life.",
            explanation:"virtue ethics is important: \n"+
            "It helps one to distinguish between right and wrong \n"+
            "Enables to become responsible and contributing members in the society \n"+
            "It helps in finding out the true purpose of life \n"+
            "It also helps in building a positive approach to things  \n"+
            "It helps to eliminate problems of social evils from oneâ€™s life"
       },
            {
            id: 7,
            question: "If Almaz develops love, respect, and kindness in her life, she develops the virtue ethics of:",
            optons:["Responsibility, Fairness, Compassion, Self-discipline" ],
            correct_option: "Compassion",
            explanation:"Compassion: is the ability to understand or feel what another person is going through from within their own frame of reference,"
        },
            {
            id: 8,
            question: "You have heard in media about Haile Gebresellase. You are imitating his life experience in your life. Haile's experience for you served as:",
            options: [
            " Role model",
            " A teacher",
            " An entrepreneur",
            " Wealthy person"
            ],
            correct_option: "Role model",
            explanation:"A role model is someone whose behavior, actions, and achievements are emulated or admired by others. \n"+
            "Role models serve as examples of desirable qualities or behaviors that others aspire to. \n"+
            "Haile Gebreselassie, as a world-renowned Ethiopian long-distance runner and Olympic gold medalist, is widely regarded as a role model for his dedication, perseverance, and athletic excellence. \n"+
            "By imitating Haile's life experience, you are likely seeking to emulate his qualities and achievements, making him your role model."
            },
            {
            id: 9,
            question: "When the power of the government concentrated at the center, the type of government is:",
            options: [
            "Unitary state",
            "Federal state",
            "Confederal state",
            "Hybrid state"
            ],
            correct_option: "Unitary state",
            explanation:"The unitary state is a type of state structure characterized by power centralization.\n"+
            "It is a type of state structur in which a single power, known as the central government, controls all aspects of government."
            },
            {
            id: 10,
            question: "Which of the following is true about federalism?",
            options: [
            " All powers are concentrated at the center",
            " It is preferable state structure for large territory and diverse society.",
            " It is helpful for uniformity of administration.",
            " It avoids conflict of authority."
            ],
            correct_option: "It is preferable state structure for large territory and diverse society.",
            explanation:"federalism allows different groups to share power over common interests.\n"+ 
            "It allows different groups of people in different parts of the country to enjoy diversity.\n"+
            "Thus, territorially large countries with diverse societies prefer federalism."
            },
            {
                id: 11,
                question: "In parliamentary system of government, the head of the government is:",
                options: [
                " The president",
                " The Monarch",
                " The King",
                " The Prime minister"
                ],
                correct_option: " The Prime minister",
                explanation:"Acabinet government or prime ministerial system of government is referred to as a parliamentary system of government."
                },
                {
                id: 12,
                question: "One of the following is not true about government.",
                options: [
                " Government is the element of the state",
                " Government materializes political power",
                " Government is permanent",
                " Government is intrinsic to human beings"
                ],
                correct_option: " Government is permanent",
                explanation:"Governments are not necessarily permanent. They can change over time due to various factors such as elections, revolutions, or constitutional reforms.\n"+ 
                "Governments may come into power and go out of power depending on the will of the people and the political system in place."
                },
                {
                id: 13,
                question: "In the absence of order and security, your complaints should focus on:",
                options: [
                " State",
                " Government",
                " People",
                " Outside force"
                ],
                correct_option: " Government",
                explanation:"The government is primarily responsible for maintaining order and security within a society.\n"+
                "It is the government's duty to establish and enforce laws, provide public safety through law enforcement agencies, and ensure the security of its citizens.\n"+
                "Therefore, if there is a lack of order and security, the government is the appropriate authority to address such issues and to whom complaints should be directed."
                },
                {
                id: 14,
                question: "In Ethiopia, the emperor was the law maker, law enforcer and adjudicator in the past. The type of regime is:",
                options: [
                " Monarchical",
                "  Republican",
                "  Military",
                " Socialist"
                ],
                correct_option: "Monarchical",
                explanation:"In Monarchial regime The emperor was the law enforcer, law maker and partly adjudicator.\n"+
                "Hence,the emperor had personalized power with unitary state structure."
                },
                {
                id: 15,
                question: "One of the following describes the weakness of the monarchial regime of Ethiopia.",
                options: [
                " The formation of continental organization in Addis Ababa.",
                " Significant role of state formation and national building.",
                " Established ministerial system of government.",
                " Ignorance of diversity of the country's peoples."
                ],
                correct_option: "Ignorance of diversity of the country's peoples.",
                explanation:"The monarchial regime of Ethiopia was weakened by its ignorance of the diversity of the country's peoples.\n"+
                "The regime was dominated by a small group of elites. "
                },
                {
                id: 16,
                question: "For the proper functioning of democracy one of the following is not significant.",
                options: [
                " Existence of the rule of law",
                " Well-structured and functioning institutions",
                " Existence of arbitrariness",
                " Broadening the base of public participation"
                ],
                correct_option: " Existence of arbitrariness",
                explanation:"Arbitrariness is the opposite of the rule of law.\n"+ 
                "It is when the government or other powerful individuals are able to act without regard for the law. This can lead to corruption, abuse of power, and a lack of accountability."
                },
                {
                    id: 17,
                    question: "Which of the following is true about supremacy of the Constitution as a principle democracy?",
                    options: [
                    " Constitution is highest law of the land.",
                    " Any codes of law of doesn't refer the country's constitution",
                    " Criminal law acts independently without reference of the constitution",
                    " Constitution is not the reference point of other laws."
                    ],
                    correct_option: " Constitution is highest law of the land.",
                    explanation:" The supremacy of the Constitution is a principle of constitutional law in the United States that establishes the Constitution as the supreme law of the land. This means that no law, including state or federal laws, can be in conflict with the Constitution."
                    },
                    {
                    id: 18,
                    question: "The separation of state and religion are clearly indicated in the FDRE constitution of Ethiopia. Which principle of democracy applied here?",
                    options: [
                    "  Principle of accountability and transparency",
                    "  Principle of citizen's participation",
                    "  Principle of secularism",
                    "  Principle of separation of powers"
                    ],
                    correct_option: "Principle of secularism",
                    explanation: 'The principle of secularism is enshrined in the FDRE constitution of Ethiopia, which states that "the state does not recognize any religion as state religion" and that "all religions are equal before the law.'
                    },
                    {
                    id: 19,
                    question: "The value of democracy which accepts differences positively is:",
                    options: [
                    "  Liberty",
                    "  Justice",
                    "  Tolerance",
                    "  Equality"
                    ],
                    correct_option: "  Tolerance",
                    explanation:" Tolerance is the ability to accept or respect the beliefs or practices of others, even if they are different from your own"
                    },
                    {
                    id: 20,
                    question: "Which of the following is true about Yajoka as an indigenous institution?",
                    options: [
                    "  The legislative and judicial functions in Gurage.",
                    "  The method of conflict resolution in Wolaita.",
                    "  The indigenous power transition in Sidama.",
                    "  The socio-cultural administration system in Wajerat.",
                    ],
                    correct_option: " The legislative and judicial functions in Gurage.",
                    explanation:" Yajoka and Gordanna is an indigenous institution in Gurague that combines legislative and judicial functions."
                    },
                    {
                        id: 21,
                        question: "Awassiya is to Wolaita society, whereas Gada is to society.",
                        options: [
                        " Amhara",
                        " Oromo",
                        " Kambata",
                        " Gurage"
                        ],
                        correct_option: " Kambata",
                       
                        explanation: "Gada is an important indigenous democratic institution in" +
                        " Oromo society. Gada is a well-known figure. The Oromo people" +
                        " use Gada as an indigenous institution of governance."
                        },
                        {
                        id: 22,
                        question: "One of the following is considered as opportunity for development of democracy in Ethiopia.",
                        options: [
                        " Absence of powerful democratic institutions.",
                        "  The absence of competing parties for power.",
                        "  Rapid expansion of education.",
                        "  Lack of an informed society."
                        ],
                        correct_option: " Rapid expansion of education.",
                        explanation:""
                        },
                        {
                        id: 23,
                        question: "Which of the following is considered as challenge for democratization process in Ethiopia?",
                        options: [
                        "  Massive investments on infrastructure such as roads and railways.",
                        "  Significant investment in agriculture and agro-industry.",
                        "  The prevalence of weak political participation.",
                        "  Private and public investment in tourism."
                        ],
                        correct_option: "  The prevalence of weak political participation.",
                        explanation:" Ethiopia has made significant progress in recent years in terms of democratization. However, there are still a number of challenges that need to be addressed in order to ensure that the country's democratic transition is sustainable. One of the most significant challenges is the prevalence of weak political participation."
                        },
                        {
                        id: 24,
                        question: "The document which contains the nation's basic and fundamental law is:",
                        options: [
                        "  Civil law",
                        "  Constitution",
                        "  Criminal law",
                        "  Commercial law"
                        ],
                        correct_option: "  Constitution",
explanation:" A constitution is a set of fundamental principles or established precedents according to which a state or other organization is acknowledged to be governed. It is a formal document outlining the principal laws and principles of the organization, and typically establishes the structure of government."
                        },
                        {
                        id: 25,
                        question: "If the government acts and decides based on the constitution, this is the expression of:",
                        options: [
                        " Arbitrariness",
                        "  Secularism",
                        "  Constitutionalism",
                        "  Anarchism"
                        ],
                        correct_option: "  Constitutionalism",
explanation:" Constitutionalism is a political philosophy based on the rule of law, which holds that the law should govern a nation as a whole, including its government. This means that the government is not above the law, and that its powers are limited by the constitution. \n" +

"Arbitrariness is the quality of being based on random choice or personal whim, rather than any reason or system.  \n" +
"Secularism is the principle of separation of church and state. Anarchism is a political philosophy that advocates for the absence of government."
                        },
                        {
                        id: 26,
                        question: "Which of the following is not true about constitution? It is:___",
                        options: [
                        " Highest law of the land",
                        "  A law behind the law.",
                        "  A blue print of the government",
                        "  It doesn't govern other laws of the country."
                        ],
                        correct_option: "It doesn't govern other laws of the country.",
explanation:" A constitution is the supreme law of the land. It is a law behind the law, and it is a blueprint of the government. It sets out the basic principles of the government, and it defines the powers of the different branches of government. It also protects the rights of the people."
                        },
                        {
                            id: 27,
                            question: "If someone reads the constitution of a country, he will have a better understanding about the overall nature of the country. This is because constitution:",
                            options: [
                            "  Describes the geographical map Of the country.",
                            "  Explains the natural resources of the country.",
                            "  Situates the location of the country.",
                            "  Defines the political ideology and structure of the country."
                            ],
                            correct_option: " Defines the political ideology and structure of the country.",
explanation:" A constitution is a document that outlines the basic principles and laws of a country. It establishes the structure of government, the rights of citizens, and the relationship between the government and the people."
                            },
                            {
                            id: 28,
                            question: "There is strong relationship between rule of law and constitutionalism. The description of this statement is:__",
                            options: [
                            "  Equality before the law will be violated.",
                            "  Citizens are treated equally before the law.",
                            "  Few individuals will be treated better than others.",
                            "  The constitution protects the ruling party better than others."
                            ],
                            correct_option: "  Citizens are treated equally before the law.",
explanation:" Rule of law is the principle that no one is above the law, and that everyone is subject to the same laws, including those in power. "
                            },
                            {
                            id: 29,
                            question: "One of the following explains the importance of constitutionalism, except:",
                            options: [
                            "  Encourages the development of democratic system.",
                            "  The rule of law prevails.",
                            "  Government power will be limited.",
                            "  Popular sovereignty will be discouraged."
                            ],
                            correct_option: "Popular sovereignty will be discouraged.",
explanation:" Constitutionalism is a system of government in which the constitution is the supreme law of the land. It is a system that limits the power of the government and protects the rights of the people."
                            },
                            {
                            id: 30,
                            question: "If the constitution is difficult to change due to its series of procedures, it is named as:",
                            options: [
                            "  Rigid constitution",
                            "  Flexible constitution",
                            "  Written constitution",
                            "  Unwritten constitution"
                            ],
                            correct_option: "Rigid constitution",
explanation:" A rigid constitution is a constitution that is difficult to change. It usually requires a supermajority vote in the legislature, or a popular referendum, to amend the constitution \n" +

"A flexible constitution is a constitution that is easy to change. It can be amended by a simple majority vote in the legislature. \n" + 

"A written constitution is a constitution that is set down in a single document. \n" +
"An unwritten constitution is a constitution that is not set down in a single document."
                            },
                            {
                                id: 31,
                                question: "The laws of the constitution are not practically implemented. This type of constitution is:",
                                options: [
                                " Effective constitution",
                                " Nominal constitution",
                                " Federal Constitution",
                                " Unitary constitution"
                                ],
                                correct_option: " Nominal constitution",
explanation:" A nominal constitution is a constitution that is not practically implemented. \n" +
 
"An effective constitution is a constitution that is followed and enforced. \n" +

"A federal constitution is a constitution that divides power between a central government and regional governments.\n" +

"A unitary constitution is a constitution that vests all power in a central government."
                                },
                                {
                                id: 32,
                                question: "There is no order and stability. Anyone who assumed himself strong kills the weaker one. The above idea states the absence of:",
                                options: [
                                "  Absence of anarchism",
                                "  Absence of arbitrariness",
                                "  Absence of constitutionalism",
                                "  Presence of constitutionalism"
                                ],
                                correct_option: " Absence of anarchism",
explanation: 'Arbitrariness is the quality of being based on random choice or personal whim, rather than any reason or system. In the context of the question, the idea that "anyone who assumed himself strong kills the weaker one" suggests that there is no order or stability, and that people are free to do whatever they want, regardless of the consequences.'
                                },
                                {
                                id: 33,
                                question: "One of the following is not categorized under First Generation Rights.",
                                options: [
                                " The Right of work",
                                "  The Right to employment",
                                " The Right to Good Living",
                                "  The Right to Life"

                                ],
                                correct_option: "The Right to employment",
explanation:" First generation rights are also known as civil and political rights. They are rights that protect individuals from government interference and ensure their participation in the political process. These rights include the right to life, liberty, and security of person"
                                },
                                {
                                id: 34,
                                question: "The right to due and fair process of law is categorized under:",
                                options: [
                                " First Generation Rights",
                                " Second Generation Rights",
                                " Third Generation Rights",
                                "  Solidarity Rights"
                                ],
                                correct_option: "First Generation Rights",
explanation:" First generation rights are also known as civil and political rights. They are rights that protect individuals from government interference and ensure their participation in the political process. These rights include the right to life, liberty, and security of person"

                                },
                                {
                                id: 35,
                                question: "One of the following rights is categorized under Solidarity Rights.",
                                options: [
                                "  The Right to be informed",
                                "  The Right to Education",
                                " The Right to just distribution of wealth",
                                "  The Right to Religious freedom."
                                ],
                                correct_option: "  The Right to just distribution of wealth",
explanation:" Solidarity rights are rights that arise from the interdependent and interrelated nature of human beings. They are based on the idea that we are all connected and that we have a responsibility to help each other. Solidarity rights include the right to development, the right to peace, and the right to a healthy environment."
                                },
{
                                    id: 36,
                                    question: "The FDRE constitution of article 25 states that all persons are equal before the law. Among the following options all are true except:",
                                    options: [
                                    "  Equality regardless of gender",
                                    "  Inequality based on belief",
                                    "  Equality regardless of social status",
                                    "  Equality regardless of language"
                                    ],
                                    correct_option: "  Inequality based on belief",
explanation:" The FDRE constitution of article 25 states that all persons are equal before the law. This means that all persons are entitled to equal protection of the law and that no person shall be discriminated against on the basis of race, sex, language, religion, political or other opinion, national or social origin, property, birth or other status."
                                    },
                                    {
                                    id: 37,
                                    correct_option: "Among Regions of Ethiopia, which regional constitution is adopted recently?",
                                 options: ["Afar","Somali","Sidama","Oromia"],
                                 correct_option:"Sidama ",
                                 explanation:" No explanation"
                                    },
                                    {
                                    id: 38,
                                    question: "One of the following statement or phrase is different from others about regional constitutions of Ethiopia.",
                                    options: [
                                    " The Right to Violate the FDRE constitution",
                                    "  The Right to life",
                                    "  The Right to security",
                                    "  The Right of accused person"
                                    ],
                                    correct_option: "  The Right to Violate the FDRE constitution",
explanation:" The right to life, the right to security, and the right of accused person are all fundamental human rights that are enshrined in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and other international human rights treaties. The right to violate the FDRE constitution, on the other hand, is not a right that is recognized by any international human rights instrument."
                                    },
                                    {
                                    id: 39,
                                    question: "Someone left his region and went to the other region of Ethiopia to get job opportunity there. However, the local administrator blocked him not to be employed there. Which right of the FDRE constitution violated here?",
                                    options: [
                                    "  The Right to liberty",
                                    " The Right to equality",
                                    "  The Right to social and economic development",
                                    "  The Right to cultural development"
                                    ],
                                    correct_option: " The Right to liberty ",
explanation:'The right to liberty is enshrined in Article 33 of the FDRE Constitution, which states that "every person has the right to liberty and security of person." This right includes the right to freedom of movement and residence'
                                    },
                                    {
                                    id: 40,
                                    question: "why should we consider early marriage as a violation of women's rights in Ethiopia? This is because of",
                                    options: [
                                    "  Population increment",
                                    " The health and physical negative effect of women.",
                                    " Stable and peaceful character of women",
                                    "  Safeguarding the virginity of females"
                                    ],
                                    correct_option: "  The health and physical negative effect of women.",
explanation:" Early marriage is a violation of women's rights in Ethiopia because it has a number of negative consequences for girls and women, including: \n" +
"	Health risks \n" +
"	Education and employment opportunities: Girls who marry early are less likely to complete their education or enter the workforce. \n" +
"	Violence and abuse: Girls who marry early are at increased risk of domestic violence and abuse. \n" +
"	Social isolation: Girls who marry early are often isolated from their friends and family. "
                                    },
                                    {
                                        id: 41,
                                        question: "One of the following is not considered as violation of human rights.",
                                        options: [
                                        "  Conflict and displacement",
                                        "  Child labor abuse",
                                        "  Poverty and inequality",
                                        "  Peaceful coexistence and tolerance"
                                        ],
                                        correct_option: "  Peaceful coexistence and tolerance",
explanation:" Human rights are rights inherent to all human beings, regardless of race, sex, nationality, ethnicity, language, religion, or any other status. Human rights include the right to life and liberty, freedom from slavery and torture, freedom of opinion and expression, the right to work and education, and many more."
                                        },
                                        {
                                        id: 42,
                                        question: "A mismatch of ideas between people who have opposing viewpoints, ideas or goals is:",
                                        options: [
                                        "  Harmony",
                                        " Conflict",
                                        "  Agreement",
                                        "  Violence"
                                        ],
                                        correct_option: "  Conflict",
explanation:" A conflict is a disagreement or argument between two or more people. It can be caused by a mismatch of ideas, viewpoints, or goals. Conflicts can be resolved through negotiation, compromise, or mediation. \n" +

"Harmony is a state of peace and agreement. It is the opposite of conflict. Agreement is a state of having the same opinion or viewpoint. It is also the opposite of conflict.  \n" +

"Violence is the use of physical force to harm someone or something. It is not the same as conflict."
                                        },
                                        {
                                        id: 43,
                                        question: "Which of the following is true about peace? It is:",
                                        options: [
                                        "  Only the absence of war",
                                        "  Only the absence of fights and violence",
                                        "  Not only the absence of war but also the presence of justice and law.",
                                        "  Only the existence of calmness"
                                        ],
                                        correct_option: " Not only the absence of war but also the presence of justice and law.",
explanation:" Peace is a state of harmony and tranquility. It is the absence of war, violence, and conflict. \n" +
"Peace is also the presence of justice and law. \n" +
"Justice is the fair and impartial treatment of all people, \n" +
"law is a system of rules that govern society."
                                        },
                                        {
                                        id: 44,
                                        question: "One of the following is true about conflict",
                                        options: [
                                        "  Equal sharing of resources",
                                        "  Fair treatment of cases",
                                        "  Avoidance of prejudice",
                                        "  Existence of prejudice and stereotypes"
                                        ],
                                        correct_option: "  Existence of prejudice and stereotypes",
explanation:" Prejudice and stereotypes are often at the root of conflict. Prejudice is a negative attitude towards a group of people based on their race, ethnicity, religion, gender, or other characteristics. " +
" Stereotypes are oversimplified generalizations about a group of people."
                                        },
                                        {
                                        id: 45, question: "In negotiation  process when both parties give up something to reach an agreement is:",
                                        options: [
                                        "  Collaboration",
                                        "  Avoidance",
                                        "  Compromise",
                                        "  Mediation"
                                        ],
                                        correct_option: "  Compromise",
explanation:" Compromise is a negotiation technique where each party gives up something in order to reach an agreement. It is a way of resolving conflict by finding a solution that is acceptable to both parties. \n" +

"Collaboration is a process where two or more people work together to achieve a common goal. It is a way of working together to solve problems and create solutions that are beneficial to everyone involved. \n" +

"Avoidance is a conflict resolution strategy where one or both parties withdraw from the conflict. It is a way of dealing with conflict by avoiding it altogether. \n" +

"Mediation is a process where a neutral third party helps two or more people resolve a conflict. The mediator's role is to help the parties communicate and find a solution that is acceptable to both sides."
                                        },
                                        {
                                            id: 46,
                                            question: "Which of the following is true about mediation?",
                                            options: [
                                            "  The mediator has decision making role",
                                            "  The mediator facilitates discussion and creates a possible environment for solution for both parties.",
                                            "  He doesn't recommend solutions.",
                                            "  All of the above"
                                            ],
                                            correct_option: "  The mediator facilitates discussion and creates a possible environment for solution for both parties.",
explanation:" Mediation is a process where a neutral third party helps two or more people resolve a conflict. The mediator's role is to help the parties communicate and find a solution that is acceptable to both sides."
                                            },
                                            {
                                            id: 47,
                                            question: "All statements describe the necessity of peace building, except:",
                                            options: [
                                            "  It encourages insecurity and instability",
                                            "  It prevents conflicts from escalating",
                                            "  It helps for the protection of lives and properties",
                                            "  It encourages the development of unity and togetherness"
                                            ],
                                            correct_option: " It encourages insecurity and instability",
explanation:" Peace building is the process of creating and maintaining peaceful relationships between people and groups. It is a long-term process that involves addressing the root causes of conflict, building trust and cooperation, and promoting reconciliation."
                                            },
                                            {
                                            id: 48,
                                            question: "One of the following is important for the prevalence of peace building in certain society.",
                                            options: [
                                            "  Tolerance",
                                            "  Intolerance",
                                            "  Disobedience",
                                            "  Homelessness"
                                            ],
                                            correct_option: "Tolerance",
explanation:"Tolerance is the ability to accept or respect the beliefs or practices of others, even if they are different from your own. It is an important value for peace building because it allows people to live together in harmony, even if they have different backgrounds or opinions."
                                            },
                                            { id: 49,
                                            question: "Which indigenous conflict resolution mechanism is practiced in Oromo Society?",
                                            options: [
                                            "  Shimgilina",
                                            "  Mada'a",
                                            "  Jaarsumma",
                                            "  Yejoka"
                                            ],
                                            correct_option: "Jaarsumma",
explanation:""
                                            },
                                            {
                                            id: 50,
                                            question: "Which comes first on problem solving process?",
                                            options: [
                                            "  Identifying causes of a problem.",
                                            "  Selecting alternative solutions",
                                            "  Implementing a solution",
                                            "  Identifying a problem"
                                            ],
                                            correct_option: "  Identifying a problem",
explanation:" The first step in the problem solving process is to identify the problem. This means clearly defining the problem and understanding its causes. Once the problem is clearly defined, you can begin to brainstorm possible solutions. "
                                            },
{
id: 51,
question: "Which comes last in problem solving model?",
options: [
"  Define the problem",
"  Determine the root causes",
"  Evaluate the outcome of the solution",
"  Implement the solution"
],
correct_option: " Evaluate the outcome of the solution",
explanation: "The problem solving model is a step-by-step process that can be used to solve any problem. The steps in the problem solving model are: \n" +

"1. Define the problem. \n" +
"2. Determine the root causes. \n" +
"3. Generate possible solutions. \n" +
"4. Evaluate the possible solutions. \n" +
"5. Implement the solution. \n" +
"6. Evaluate the outcome of the solution" 
},

{
id: 52,
question: "'Knowing the problem is solving half of the problem.'  This statement describes the",
options: [
"  Determining the root causes of the problem",
"  Defining the problem",
"  Selecting a solution",
"  Developing alternative solutions"
],
correct_option: "Defining the problem",
explanation: 'The statement "Knowing the problem is solving half of the problem" describes the importance of defining the problem before trying to solve it. \n' +

"Determining the root causes of the problem is important, but it's not the same as defining the problem. The root cause is the underlying issue that's causing the problem, but the problem itself is the specific issue that needs to be solved. \n" +

"Selecting a solution is the next step in the problem-solving process, but it can't be done until you've clearly defined the problem. \n" +

"Developing alternative solutions is a good way to come up with a creative solution, but it's also important to have a clear understanding of the problem before you start brainstorming."
},

{
id: 53,
question: "Which step comes first in critical thinking for decision making process?",
options: [
"  Identify the decision",
"  Gather relevant information",
"  Weighing the evidence",
"  Identify the alternatives"
],
correct_option: "  Identify the decision",
explanation:" The first step in critical thinking for decision making process is to identify the decision. This means clearly defining the problem or issue that needs to be addressed. "
},

{
id: 54,
Question: "After gathering of information in decision making process, possible courses of action will be identified. This step of decision making process is:",
Options: [
"  Gathering relevant information",
"  Weighing the evidence",
"  Taking action",
"Identification of alternatives"
],
correct_option: "Identification of alternatives",
explanation:" After gathering relevant information, the next step in the decision making process is to identify possible courses of action. \n" +
"This involves brainstorming all of the possible options that could be taken to address the problem or opportunity at hand. \n" +
"Once a list of alternatives has been generated, they can then be evaluated and compared to one another in order to select the best course of action."
},

{
id: 55,
question: "The skills of critical thinking which is the ability to understand and express the significance of a wide range of experiences and situations is:",
options: [
"  Assessing the credibility",
"  Comprehending and expressing",
"  Identifying the relationships",
"  Self-regulation"
],
correct_option: "  Comprehending and expressing",
explanation:" Comprehending and expressing is a skill of critical thinking which is the ability to understand and express the significance of a wide range of experiences and situations."
},
{
id: 56,
question: "The habit of critical thinking which is not important for problem solving is:",
options: [
"  Judgments based on personal preference rather than evidence.",
"  Uses evidence skillfully and impartially",
"  Strive for understanding",
"  Try to be well informed and open minded."
],
correct_option: "Judgments based on personal preference rather than evidence.",
explanation:" Critical thinking is the ability to think clearly and rationally about what to do or what to believe. It includes the ability to engage in reflective and independent thinking. \n" +
"Someone with critical thinking skills are: \n" +

"* Understand the logical connections between ideas \n" +
"* Identify, construct and evaluate arguments \n" +
"* Detect inconsistencies and common mistakes in reasoning \n" +
"* Solve problems systematically \n" +
"* Make sound decisions \n" +
"* Communicate effectively"
}, 
{
id: 57,
question: "If we encourage students to solve problems by repetitive attempts, the strategy of critical thinking is:",
options: [
"  Trial and error methods",   
"  Creating mental images the barriers",
" Understanding",
"  Manipulative"
],
correct_option: " Trial and error methods ",
explanation:" Trial and error is a problem-solving method that involves trying different solutions until one is found that works. It is a common method used by children and novices, but it can also be used by experts when there is no other obvious solution."
},
{
id: 58,
question: "One of the following is not true about critical thinking? It helps to:-",
options: [
" Become independent and self-directed thinkers and learners.",
"  Overcome personal preconceptions and biases.",
"  Discourage reasonable and intelligent decisions",   
"  Use and draw on evidence to justify your own arguments"
],
correct_option: "  Discourage reasonable and intelligent decisions",
explanation: 'The statement "Critical thinking helps to discourage reasonable and intelligent decisions" is not true. Critical thinking is actually the opposite of this. It is a way of thinking that helps us to make better decisions by thinking clearly and rationally about the information we have.'
},
{
id: 59,
question: "Which of the following is true about critical thinking?",
options: [
"  Uses evidence for justification of arguments",
"  It motivates irrational thought",   
"  It discourages the ability of thinking",   
"  It is irrelevant for development of human beings",   
],
correct_option: "  Uses evidence for justification of arguments",
explanation:" Critical thinking is important because it allows us to make better decisions and to be more informed citizens. \n" +
"It also helps us to avoid being misled by false information and to be more open-minded to new ideas."
},
{
id: 60,
question: "If the student solves the existing problem by the new solution, the critical thinking strategy used is:",
options: [
"  Identifying multiple solutions",
"  Monitoring a solution",
"  Creating mental images",
"  Considering unusual viewpoints"
],
correct_option: "  Identifying multiple solutions",
explanation:" In the given scenario, the student is able to solve the existing problem by coming up with a new solution. This shows that the student is able to identify multiple solutions to a problem. This is a critical thinking skill that is important for success in school and in life."
}
]


                                        
                                        
                                    
                                    
                                
                                
                            
                            
     
